<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-27T00:55:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ryan Yang-Liu’s Website</title><subtitle>Ryan Yang-Liu, MIT 2027. Physics &amp; CS.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">There are 2048 Ways To Solve a Rubiks Cube</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/12/25/rubiks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There are 2048 Ways To Solve a Rubiks Cube" /><published>2023-12-25T09:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-25T09:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/12/25/rubiks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/12/25/rubiks.html"><![CDATA[<p>No, this isn’t going to be some whimsical list of different strategies, starting with F2L and slowly descending into insanity. 2048 is way too big of a number for that. I’m nowhere near that creative.</p>

<p>Rather, there are literally 2048 different, technically distinct orientations of a rubik’s cube that “solve” the puzzle and are visually correct, but are nevertheless different.</p>

<p>Namely, if you draw an arrow on each sticker of the rubik’s cube to keep track of its position, you can track the precise orientation of each of the pieces. In a perfectly solved cube, each of the edge and corner stickers are perfectly fixed because they have to be oriented to be adjacent to a specified other side. But! The center faces actually have no such requirement, and are free (ish) to move.</p>

<p>Thus, in theory, there are a total of 4^6 different orientations: each of the centers has four different orientations, and there are six centers. However the real number ends up being half of this: 2048.</p>

<h2 id="part-1-there-are-at-most-2048--12--46-orientations">Part 1: There are at most 2048 = 1/2 * 4^6 orientations</h2>
<p>Let \(\mathbb{Z}_4\) be the set {0,1,2,3} taken mod 4. Thus, the orientation of the set of six centers is a 6d vector, where each value is a number in {0,1,2,3}, with the assumption that (0,0,0,0,0,0) is our baseline solution.</p>

<p>Then, to demonstrate \(\leq 2048\), we claim that it must be true that the sum of the orientations of each of the faces must be invariant mod 180 degrees, or the sum of the values in \((\{0,1,2,3\})^6\) are 0 mod 2. This is equivalent to saying that any sequences of moves that sends a color-solved rubik’s cube back to itself must have an even number of moves, where each move is a 90 degree rotation of one face.</p>

<p>Inspired by Cayley’s Theorem, we consider every action to be a permutation of S_54, the group reorienting the (6 faces) * (9 stickers/face) = 54 stickers.</p>

<p>For reasons known to literature, each “move” is an “odd” permutation since it is composed of five 4-cycles. Then, in order to get back to the identity, which is even, there must have been an even number of cycles (otherwise odd times odd would’ve been even).</p>

<h2 id="part-2-all-2048-orientations-with-even-total-sum-can-be-achieved">Part 2: All 2048 orientations with even total sum can be achieved.</h2>

<p>To show this, we demonstrate two possible sequences of moves that achieve:</p>

<p>Type A, (2,0,0,0,0,0):</p>
<ul>
  <li>Namely, there is a sequence of moves that rotates one face 180 degrees: 5x (R, U, R’, U). - Source: https://www.reddit.com/r/Rubiks_Cubes/comments/kduwle/comment/gg008h2/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3</li>
</ul>

<p>Type B, (1,-1,0,0,0,0):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Namely, there exists a sequence of moves that rotates one face 90 degrees cw, and an adjacent face 90 degrees ccw.</li>
  <li>Source: http://tilde.club/~notfire/cube/3x3x3_x_rotating_centres.htm</li>
</ul>

<p>We claim that this forms a basis of all even-sum elements in the set {0,1,2,3 mod 4}^6. Type A moves reduce the problem to just handling {0,1}, and then if X and Y are a pair of opposite sides, with the other four being A, B, C, D, then the following five Type B moves are linearly independent:</p>
<ul>
  <li>XA, XB, XC, XD, YA</li>
</ul>

<p>This covers all 32 even-sum vectors in \(\{0,1\}^6\), since:</p>

<ul>
  <li>orientation of Y determines number of YAs.</li>
  <li>orientation of A, B,C,D then determine numbers of XA, XB,XC,XDs.</li>
</ul>

<p>Thus, (2,0,0,0,0,0) and (1,-1,0,0,0,0) cover all even sum elements of \(\{0,1,2,3\}^6\).</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>In summary, it is possible to rotate the center faces by a cumulative even number of 90-degree turns, for a total of 2048 ways to solve a Rubik’s cube.</p>

<p>Remarkably, I can not find any reference to this on the internet. The idea here is mainly just the pairing of the two known-ish ideas of:</p>

<ul>
  <li>even number of moves implying multiple of 180 net center</li>
  <li>the known center shifting algorithms</li>
</ul>

<p>into a tight/precise full characterization of reachable center-orientation systems.</p>

<p><em>In case of conflict over primacy, I figured this out on December 25th, 2023.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[No, this isn’t going to be some whimsical list of different strategies, starting with F2L and slowly descending into insanity. 2048 is way too big of a number for that. I’m nowhere near that creative.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nineteen</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/19/nineteen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nineteen" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/19/nineteen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/19/nineteen.html"><![CDATA[<!-- ---
layout: post
title:  "Turning 19"
date:   2023-11-16 20:50:32 -0400
categories: jekyll update, essay
--- -->

<p>I’m turning 19 tomorrow. 6938 days. 166512 hours. 599,443,200 seconds.</p>

<p>Last year, I spent my 18th birthday writing essays in the morning, and</p>

<p>I’ll be twenty next time. We’re on the up and up.</p>

<p>Last night as I was walking back from an AI reading group I’m in, I was telling a friend about this paper I had just read, that there’s a degree of true randomness in what metabolites get activated in your brain, and there is something called true love.</p>

<p>I think this is the first full year of my life I went without truly falling in love. I think that changes a person. I stopped feeling. I stopped being vulnerable?</p>

<p>I wish I was a better writer. Paul Graham, Ben Kuhn, all of these people who can just</p>

<p>A friend asked me if I was a performer or an observer.</p>

<p>… and I can’t believe I wrote this in VSCode.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">College</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/17/college.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="College" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/17/college</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/12/17/college.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Baby Boys: The Mystery of Nauru’s At-Birth Sex Ratio</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/11/16/Nauru.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Baby Boys: The Mystery of Nauru’s At-Birth Sex Ratio" /><published>2023-11-16T19:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-16T19:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/11/16/Nauru</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2023/11/16/Nauru.html"><![CDATA[<p>From ~2015 to 2020, the Republic of Nauru seems to have had the world’s lowest at-birth sex ratio at ~0.84, one of two countries with more girls than boys.</p>

<p>And for some reason, I couldn’t find ANY news coverage explaining this? So, I set out to solve this mystery on my own, and here are the results of my internet sleuthing:</p>

<p>(pre-TLDR; low confidence that maybe phosphorus/obesity somehow affects baby gender or the @cia messed up their data, with a nice Covid epilogue)</p>

<p><strong>I: Historical Context</strong></p>

<p>Nauru is an island in Oceania approximately halfway between Australia and Hawaii. Previously mostly ignored by Europe, in 1899, high-grade phosphate ore was discovered in Nauru [1]. Occupied in sequence by Germany, Australia, and Japan, Nauru finally gained independence in 1968 after having been stripped of 35 trillion metric tons of phosphate.</p>

<p><strong>II: Biology: a la Alec Jones and “the water’s turning the frogs gay.”</strong></p>

<p>Due to the destruction of the natural land, 90% of the food in Nauru is imported [2], and Nauru has a 61% prevalence of obesity, the highest in the world (USA has 36.2%) [3].</p>

<p>It’s known that the environment can have an impact on the sex ratio of births. For turtles, gender is determined by temperature during incubation. More relevantly, male billionaires have an incredible 2X more sons than daughters [4].</p>

<p>Thus, it’s <em>possible</em> that the literal presence of phosphorus, or more likely the obesity epidemic that came as an aftereffect of environmental degradation, may have had an effect on the sex ratio.</p>

<p>Frustratingly, social scientists have not done any research into the effect of obesity on at-birth sex ratios, despite the insane coincidence that the country with the lowest at-birth sex ratio also has the highest rates of obesity.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s just bad data?</p>

<p><strong>III: The CIA World Factbook</strong></p>

<p>The ratio over time (by default m/f) has been:
2013 Nauru Bureau of Stats*: 193/173=1.11 [5]
2017 CIA Factbook: 0.83 [6]
2020 CIA Factbook: 0.84 [7]
2022 CIA Factbook: 1.04 [8]</p>

<p>Weird in 2017/2020, but back to normal in 2022?</p>

<p>The sample size is small, but not <em>that</em> small. At ~300 births a year, each of the individual 2017 and 2020 sex ratios has a p-value of ~0.04, and damningly, the 0-14 age block also had a 0.79 ratio with 1337 males to 1684 females.</p>

<p>Additionally, it’s almost literally impossible to reconcile the change in the 0-14 block from the 2020 and 2022 data:</p>
<ul>
  <li>0.84-&gt;1.04 (at birth)</li>
  <li>0.79 -&gt; 1.04 (0-14 block)</li>
  <li>0.85 -&gt; 0.91 (15-24)
without massive changes in measured populations due to something like, say, a pandemic.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>IV: A Clue: Covid?</strong></p>

<p>I came across Nauru’s notable at-birth sex-ratio back in 2021 and was hopeful that the return to normal in 2022 could explain this mystery.</p>

<p>It sort of does. On one hand, the return to a 1:1 ratio in the 0-14 and 15-24 blocks are explainable by Covid. New Zealand and Australia, popular places for Nauru residents to find employment, enforced strict Covid bubbles, likely forcing the mostly male migrant workers to stay in Nauru, restoring the ratio.</p>

<p>But the at-birth sex ratio is not solved by COVID at all???? It’s <em>supposed</em> to be 50:50 no matter what, with my only ideas being:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The CIA collected bad data in 2017/2020 and didn’t bother sanity-checking the insane 0.84 at-birth sex ratio.</li>
  <li>Related to the previous, but maybe a small group of Nauru people have been hiding their boys from the CIA?</li>
  <li>Nauru people do ultrasounds pre-pregnancy and travel to the mainland for the births of the, generally larger, male babies.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>V: Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>Recap: Nauru’s natural landscape got messed up. Health and environment can affect gender, and Nauru’s environment and health were seriously affected by phosphorus mining. While COVID explains the sex ratio in the 0-14 block, the at-birth sex ratio should not be affected, but it nevertheless jumped significantly from 2017/2020 to 2022, rising from ~0.8 to ~1.</p>

<p>My plan is now to reach out to Nauru officials to see if they know anything, but any help in solving the following still-open problems would be greatly appreciated:</p>

<p>1) Could obesity rates actually cause such a big change in the at-birth sex ratio?
2) Are there any COVID-era changes that could affect the at-birth sex ratio, such as an increase in the survival rate of Nauru baby boys?
3) What are the CIA Handbook’s data-collection policies, and is it possible that they forgot to sanity-check the Nauru numbers?</p>

<p>thx for reading!  &lt;3</p>

<h2 id="sources">Sources:</h2>
<p>[1] <a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/dark-history-nauru/">https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/dark-history-nauru/</a></p>

<p>[2] https://fao.org/3/av263e/av263e.pdf</p>

<p>[3] https://wisevoter.com/country-rankings/most-obese-countries/ (#2 Palau has a healthy sex ratio of 1.07)</p>

<p>[4] https://ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2614476/</p>

<p>[5] Wikipedia’s Source is no longer accessible, but it’s in a footnote in https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Health_in_Nauru</p>

<p>[6] https://web.archive.org/web/20190109031519/https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/351.html</p>

<p>[7] https://cia.gov/the-world-factbook/about/archives/2021/field/sex-ratio/</p>

<p>[8] https://cia.gov/the-world-factbook/about/archives/2022/field/sex-ratio/</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From ~2015 to 2020, the Republic of Nauru seems to have had the world’s lowest at-birth sex ratio at ~0.84, one of two countries with more girls than boys.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basketball</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/22/basketball.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basketball" /><published>2022-04-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/22/basketball</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/22/basketball.html"><![CDATA[<p>https://www.coursehero.com/lit/Moneyball/quotes/</p>

<p>“The sheer quantity of brain power that hurled itself voluntarily and quixotically into the search for new baseball knowledge was either exhilarating or depressing, depending on how you felt about baseball. The same intellectual resources might have cured the common cold, or put a man on Pluto.”</p>

<p>“One absolutely cannot tell, by watching, the difference between a .300 hitter and a .275 hitter. The difference is one hit every two weeks.”</p>

<p>“Baseball is a soap opera that lends itself to probabilistic thinking. [Dick Cramer]”</p>

<p>“Anti-intellectual resentment is common in all of American life and it has many diverse expressions. Refusing to draft college players might have been one of them.</p>

<p>“What baseball managers did do, on occasion, beginning in the early 1980s, was hire some guy who knew how to switch on the computer. But they did this less with honest curiosity than in the spirit of a beleaguered visitor to Morocco hiring a tour guide: pay off one so that the seventy-five others will stop trying to trade you their camels for your wife. Which one you pay off is largely irrelevant.”</p>

<p>“For a lot of the players it was their first exposure to the Southern female - the most flagrant cheater in the mutual disarmament pact known as feminism. Lipstick! Hairdos! Submissiveness!”</p>

<p>“The author refers to a player’s affected nonchalance and comments he is, “too young to realize you are what you pretend to be.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[https://www.coursehero.com/lit/Moneyball/quotes/]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Superbowl</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/potw/2022/02/13/superbowl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Superbowl" /><published>2022-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/potw/2022/02/13/superbowl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/potw/2022/02/13/superbowl.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="potw" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heat-Optimal Sleep</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/02/08/heatsleep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heat-Optimal Sleep" /><published>2022-02-08T19:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-08T19:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/02/08/heatsleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/02/08/heatsleep.html"><![CDATA[<!-- ![image-title-here](../assets/flow640am.png){:class="img-responsive"} -->

<p>In a very well-done piece of data visualization showing the daily schedules of 1000 average Americans from <a href="https://flowingdata.com/2015/12/15/a-day-in-the-life-of-americans/">Flowing Data</a>, one learns that half of all Americans awake by 6:40. At MIT, the median sleep time is around 2-3AM, and attendance at 10AM classes is pretty spotty; average wakeup time is probably around 10:30 to 11:00.</p>

<p>Why is this?</p>

<p>Clearly there’s a generational disconnect here. Explaining why older people wake up around dawn is not too hard. They wake up early because they have to wake up early. But explaining why teenagers nowadays wake up later is much harder, and the oft-quoted “teenagers go to sleep later” due to pubescent hormones only has an effect of one to two hours (cite).</p>

<p>This essay will first discuss the sleep schedules of three time periods of humanity, then explain why our sleep schedules consistently slide later, and finally propose a big-if-true idea of how to fix sleep schedules without needing to rely on alarms and corporate mandates.</p>

<p>We’ll start by estabilishing a structure within which to think about sleep and circadian rhythym. Following in the steps of sleep research, we claim that the only things that really matter and consistently follow a 24-hour cycle are:</p>
<ul>
  <li>light levels</li>
  <li>temperature</li>
</ul>

<p>Then, we will, in order, consider three different kinds of lifestyles.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Early Industrial Society: Light and Heat are both scarce.</li>
  <li>Hunter-Gatherer Society: Heat is more scarce.</li>
  <li>Current Day: Neither are scarce.</li>
</ol>

<p>Important timeline landmarks to have in mind are the sequential occurrences of:</p>
<ul>
  <li>prehistoric: discovery of crude heating through fire</li>
  <li>1883: the invention of the electric thermostat</li>
  <li>1925: half of all homes switch over from gas lights/candles to electric power.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="early-industrial-society">Early Industrial Society</h4>
<p>In early industrial society, work is king. To work your 12-hour shifts, you need to be able to see. But getting light is hard! I mean come on, someone has to go out and slay sea leviathans for their blubber, and they’ll want to be handsomely compensated.</p>

<p>Thus, you need to use all of the available light. This means being awake from dawn to dusk. Then, since the evening is more comfortable, we recover the traditional conceived sleep schedule from like 9PM to dawn.</p>

<h4 id="hunter-gatherers">Hunter Gatherers</h4>

<p>I’ll be mainly referencing a paper by <em>Yetish et al.</em> from 2015 published in <a href="https://www.cell.com/current-biology/fulltext/S0960-9822(15)01157-4">Cell</a>. Within this study, they aggregated collected sleep data from three Hunter-Gatherer societies: the Tsimane, Hadza, and San. The Tsimane are in South America, and the Hadza and San are in sub-Saharan Africa, with San being the furthest from the equator among all three tribes.</p>

<p>The sleep schedules for all of the tribes <em>broadly</em> goes along the lines of “go to sleep around 3 hours after sunset and wake up around sunrise.” For all tribes, their bed time varies heavily, while their wakeup time remains highly consistent.</p>

<p>The most interesting data comes from the San, the southernmost tribe, who therefore have the largest seasonal shift. While other tribes always awake before dawn, for the San, it’s seasonal:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Summer: Awake 1hr after sunrise. Go to sleep at 10:44PM</li>
  <li>Winter: Awaken before sunrise. Go to sleep at 9:16PM.</li>
</ul>

<p>The presence of heat as a relevant variable that changes throughout the year differentiates the San sleep schedule. The other two tribes always awake before dawn, whereas San wake up after sunrise in the summer. Additionally, the San sleep more in the winter than in the summer with the same absolute wakeup time but later bedtime (a heat-dependence that doesn’t exist in modern Western society presumably due to central heating).</p>

<p>Most interestingly, the researchers found that the best way to predict wake up time is with the principle that <strong>“wake onset occurred near the nadir (minimum) of the daily temperature rhythm”</strong>. For context, the general temperature profile of Earth is that:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Temperature spikes at Dawn</li>
  <li>Temperature slowly increases afterwards and peaks at 3PM, but is mostly flat from 10AM to 5PM</li>
  <li>Slow, gradual continuous decrease from 5PM to around dawn.</li>
</ul>

<p>And this is why the San wake up later in the summer. Due to the solar schedule, the coldest time of the day gets shifted to after sunrise. An evolutionary explanation for why humans want to wake up when it’s coldest is that we want to be asleep, with its associated decreased core temperature, during the coldest part of the night.</p>

<p>Strikingly, this tells us that in the pristine state of original humanity, the main signal we use for waking up is temperature. This also helps explain why Hunter-Gatherer bedtime varies so much; the temperature decrease at night is relatively continuous and nonabrupt, allowing for high variance in when this signal fully kicks in. A light-dominated sleep-signal would guarantee a consistent bedtime, but the hours-long-delay in melatonin precludes this.</p>

<h3 id="modern-day">Modern Day</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Comfortable modern sleep is an unnatural superstimulus <a href="https://guzey.com/theses-on-sleep/#comfortable-modern-sleep-is-an-unnatural-superstimulus-sleepiness-just-like-hunger-is-normal">(Alexey Guzey)</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So what’s up with our current sleep schedules. Well, nowadays, both light and heat are largely held constant, and this ends up applying constant delaying pressure to our circadian rhythym. Recall that the signals we used to rely on were from the 2x2 matrix of:</p>
<ul>
  <li>(dawn, temp): the cold bite of pre-dawn</li>
  <li>(dawn, light): bright lights in our eyes</li>
  <li>(dusk, temp): decreasing night temperature</li>
  <li>(dusk, light): hours-delayed melatonin</li>
</ul>

<p>And so essentially, all of these have been disturbed by modern life. Everyone already sorta knows about the light things – we’re not suppose to look at blue lights before going to bed, and sunrise lamps were quite chic a few years ago.</p>

<p>The heat side is an underdiscussed equal partner though. And in fact, as seen with the tribes, their wakeup time was almost entirely determined by subtle temperature changes their bodies sensed at the temperature nadir of the day – even if this meant sometimes awakening before civil dawn in complete darkness and sometimes awakening an hour after sunrise.</p>

<h4 id="actionables">Actionables</h4>

<p>So, just maybe, the way to solve our messed up sleep schedules is temperature? Big if true at the very least.</p>

<p>For the evening, it’s already mostly solved. Anyone who’s thought about sleep knows that getting a special chilled bed or setting the thermostat lowers helps a lot.</p>

<p>But, the truly missing square from the 2x2 matrix of (dawn/dusk, light/temperature) is the <em>temperature at dawn</em> category. Ironically, this was also <strong>the strongest signal in hunter-gatherer sleep schedules</strong> since their bedtimes varied heavily, with the main checkpoint being a consistent wakeup time which was determined by “waking up at the temperature minimum.”</p>

<p>Thus, the main corollary of this systemization of what influences circadian rhythym is that we should experiment with using temperature to wake ourselves up. There’s something to be said about this idea’s similarity with the classic bucket of ice water to the face.</p>

<p>More tastefully though, it would be cool to set a consistent morning alarm where, instead of playing a sound, it would commit a tactical chilling through a smart mattress or a programmed temperature decrease setting in a thermostat.</p>

<p>Maybe I’ll build this. But for now, I sleep.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Long Weekend</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/02/08/Long-Weekend.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Long Weekend" /><published>2022-02-08T19:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-08T19:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/02/08/Long-Weekend</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/02/08/Long-Weekend.html"><![CDATA[<p>I know that it’s Tuesday, which might not look like part of the weekend. However, this weekend was a long weekend and I had Monday and Tuesday off, so I think this counts as being part of the weekend.</p>

<hr />
<p>I’ve been trying to put together a reference document, tentatively named “Practical Convex Optimization,” that can act as a bit of prologue and/or reference document for work I’ve done in optimization theory. This has turned out to be a far larger endeavor than I expected, but here’s a draft: 
<img src="https://www.overleaf.com/read/hxvvjwbmsvgw" alt="https://www.overleaf.com/read/hxvvjwbmsvgw" /></p>

<h2 id="upcoming-week">Upcoming Week</h2>
<p><img src="assets/214216meme" alt="image" /></p>

<p>For some reason, my to-do list has a massive bulge in the 2/14-216 period. It’s some sort of weird magnet for things to handle that defies logic – @RogerPenrose you might want to take a look at this, could inspire a new physics or something.</p>

<p>There’s some human things</p>
<ul>
  <li>A couple of election statements</li>
  <li>A prefect application</li>
  <li>A school meeting announcement for a Wordle Tournament (!)</li>
  <li>Valentine’s Day</li>
</ul>

<p>But then there’s also the F=ma and AIME. By some unlucky coincidence, Choate is doing both the F=ma B and AIME 2, which means that they’re on back to back days.</p>

<p>This is technically pretty likely – both {A &amp; 1} and {B &amp; 2} cause this to happen – but I feel like most schools are doing {B &amp; 1} which is significantly nicer.</p>

<h2 id="aime-and-how-the-imo-tst-process-works">AIME and how the IMO TST Process Works</h2>
<p>AIME is terrifying because it’s the first of two make-or-break contests, the second being USAMO 2022, for entering the TST process for IMO 2023.</p>

<p>The IMO TST process is complicated, see <a href="https://blog.evanchen.cc/2020/11/10/usa-special-team-selection-test-series-for-imo-2021/">Evan Chen’s Explanation of the 2021 IMO TST</a>. This year it’s also slightly different because of Covid, so perhaps there is some value in me writing an explanation of this year’s process too because the only people who understand it seem to be the people who have qualified for the process and learn it by doing it.</p>

<p>Regardless, the AIME is pretty damn important if I want to make the IMO. I need a 11 out of 15 to be safe (which would give a 240.5 USAMO index). This should be fine since I got a 14 last year – but I also spent a large chunk of my winter last year vibing to music and math.</p>

<h2 id="fma">F=ma</h2>
<p>As for F=ma, I probably won’t prep too much, maybe one or two practice sets. I qualified last year by the slimmest of margins, getting exactly the cutoff score only after they accepted a second answer for a broken problem. I don’t have high hopes for F=ma, but I’ll probably try to make time because a second USAPhO qualification would be pretty cool. Still, I care <em>much</em> more about qualifying for USAMO because I can actually do well on USAMO, not so much for USAPhO.</p>

<hr />
<p>I’m going to try to be more punctual about next week’s blog post, I think it’ll be on treating school like a day job (which \(\neq\) slacking).</p>

<p>Logistically, I’ll also mention that I’m going to add the date to the titles of all of my blog posts, as well as these nice “previous” and “next” buttons that let you move through posts on Wordpress.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I know that it’s Tuesday, which might not look like part of the weekend. However, this weekend was a long weekend and I had Monday and Tuesday off, so I think this counts as being part of the weekend.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life Update 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/01/30/Life-Update-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life Update 2" /><published>2022-01-30T19:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-30T19:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/01/30/Life-Update-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/news/2022/01/30/Life-Update-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>I originally planned on writing out a full explanation of the research in the paper that we submitted to ICML last Friday. However, since we uploaded to Arxiv at 10pm on Friday, and the verification process is slower over the weekends, I still don’t have a nice arxiv link to put in the post.</p>

<p>More importantly though, Wordpress doesn’t have LaTeX functionality, which makes any attempt at explaining math beyond arithmetic an extremely painful endeavor…</p>

<p>Instead, I’m going to write a Life Update, the second half of which will kinda be about the paper because it was <em>the</em> thing that I worked on and thought about in the week before the Jan 27 (AOE midnight) deadline.</p>

<p>I’ve also set up a mailing list, so if you enter your email into the “subscribe to our newsletter” form on the main page I’ll email you each time I post.</p>

<h2 id="week-3-sun-116---sat-122">Week 3: Sun 1/16 - Sat 1/22</h2>
<p>Hours: 9:40 (U), 10:00 (M), 9:30 (T), 12:35 (W), 10:00 (R), 13:00 (F), 10:10 (S)</p>

<p>For the first half of the week, I was still somewhat recovering from getting sick (which you can read about it in my previous life update). The period from Monday to Thursday was a delightful return to normal. After being sick for a week, and suffering through the accompanied decrease in quality of life, it was amazing being back to normal. I promised myself that I would appreciate my regained health, and I did. All in all, I lost ten pounds (mostly water) through the process. However, getting sick was a net positive on my mental health (?). It was a forced break where I didn’t think about complicated things – I thought a lot about god and pain.</p>

<p>Beginning on Friday though, the ICML paper grind began. It’s amazing how the days can be filled up; that day, I went to my Friday classes, winter rowing, ran physics club, made an amazing poster w/ Deven Huang, and then spent the rest of the night trying to solve the fact that I did not have a full convergence proof for our ICML submission.</p>

<p>On Saturday, the only thing I did was work on the paper, and this mainly took the form of me rereading papers. Throughout the entire process, I mainly referenced three papers, and I’ll reveal them in my full post about the paper. :)</p>

<h2 id="week-4-sun-123---sat-129">Week 4: Sun 1/23 - Sat 1/29</h2>
<p>Hours: 10:00 (U), 14:20 (M), 12:00 (T), 13:30 (W), 13:35 (R), 9:10 (F), 8:30 (S)</p>

<p>There are very few times in my logs when I was not-resting for more than 14 hours. Those were:</p>
<ul>
  <li>2/18/2021 (14:30): Making my first ever podcast</li>
  <li>3/1/2020 (14:00): Doing a USACO on a Monday</li>
  <li>6/17/2021 (14:40): Taking AP CSA and then an official MOP Mock IMO, with Greenish in the afternoon</li>
</ul>

<p>Hitting 14 hours is a momentous occasion. After all, 14 hours + 8 hours of sleep + 3 hours of life essentials requires 100% efficiency plus a little extra.</p>

<p>The period from Monday to Thursday when I made the most progress on the paper. I made an observation that put me in the right direction on Thursday at 10:30am while in Physics class, and then made the crucial observation at around 11:30am while in a SAC study room with DH. Thankfully, by some miracle, I didn’t have too much homework this week. Or maybe since I was sleeping less and had on average 13 hours of working time on my hands each day the homework load seemed really light.</p>

<p>I also think that I’ve mastered the art of handling midnight AOE times as an East coast person. Thursday at 11:59pm in AOE time is equal to Friday at 7am in EST time, so the technique I’ve used in my past two paper deadlines is to sleep from ~2:30 AM - ~5:00 AM. This is the perfect timing because you get a long block of time until 2:30 AM, and then wake up with a fresh mind, sync up with your collaborators, and then do a final 1.5 hours of grammar checking and higher quality edits since you’re slightly less sleep-deprived.</p>

<p>On Friday after submitting at 7am, I slept from 7:00-8:30 since I didn’t have classes until 9:20 AM. I got through classes and sports with only one person, HD, remarking about me looking tired, which I think is a great endorsement of the 2:45am - 5:15am nap as opposed to a full all-nighter. I took Friday night off, watched movies with C, went to the Lunar Banquet, and got home to Easton around 10pm, where I worked on the Arxiv version until 12:30am and then went to sleep. I slept in until noon on Saturday.</p>

<h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>While I lucked out and there wasn’t too much homework last week, God’s compensating for that this week.</p>

<p>I have</p>
<ul>
  <li>a presentation on the Froude number</li>
  <li>a history essay</li>
  <li>an English essay</li>
  <li>a personal narrative for my college counselor.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m pretty excited though, if I can stay as efficient as I was in the week before the ICML deadline, I should be able to handle everything. Contestwise, I skipped USACO this weekend because I just didn’t have enough time, and AIME is terrifyingly only two weeks away.</p>

<p>Remarkably, this post only took 1 hour, and I really should get back to homework.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I originally planned on writing out a full explanation of the research in the paper that we submitted to ICML last Friday. However, since we uploaded to Arxiv at 10pm on Friday, and the verification process is slower over the weekends, I still don’t have a nice arxiv link to put in the post.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mathematical Power of Self-Consistent Measurements (Global Combinatorics)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/01/23/Double-Counting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mathematical Power of Self-Consistent Measurements (Global Combinatorics)" /><published>2022-01-23T19:50:32-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-23T19:50:32-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/01/23/Double-Counting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/jekyll/update,/essay/2022/01/23/Double-Counting.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>sabbe saṅkhārā aniccā 
(All conditioned things are impermanent)
- Buddha</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One of the most beautiful parts of mathematics is that once you construct an object, it is truly permanent, and self-consistent to measurement. This property of mathematics is taken advantage of by a mathematically technique called “considering global values.” [1] This post will outline the basic mathematical techniques, and then pivot to interesting non-mathematical application where the technique is still true up to approximation.</p>

<h1 id="part-1">Part 1</h1>

<p>This general trick is referred to in a number of ways:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Counting in two ways</li>
  <li>Global ideas</li>
</ul>

<p>And the following mathematical ideas are special cases of the more general principle:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Swapping the order of summation</li>
  <li>Linearity of Expectation</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="canonical-math-example-1-of-2-pecking-decks">Canonical Math Example (1 of 2): Pecking Decks</h2>
<p>I’d like to start with the example that first exposed me to this idea</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>In a barn, 100 chicks sit peacefully in a circle. Suddenly, each chick randomly pecks the chick immediately to its left or right. What is the expected number of unpecked chicks? (<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/15/us/math-counts-national-competition.html">MATHCOUNTS 2017</a>)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The direct solution is to apply the “Linearity of Expectation.” The argument there would be that the probability that any individual chick is pecked is 1/4, so each pick is expected to contribute “1/4” to the number of unpecked chicks. This is true for all 100 chicks, for a total expectation of 25 unpecked chicks.</p>

<p>But there’s something deeper happening here. There is a very deep and fundamental idea which is that objects exist and have permanence.</p>

<p>For this problem, consider all $2^100$ different multiverses, where each chick pecks left or right. Then, consider the number of (unpecked chick, multiverse) pairs. Let $X$ be the number of such pairs.</p>

<p>This is a degenerate case so this first method is weirder than normal. Nevertheless, let $Y$ be the expected number of unpecked chicks in some universe. Then, $2^{100}\cdot Y$ should be the total number of (unpecked chicks, multiverse) pairs.</p>

<p>So now let’s count it in a second way. Consider a specific chick A. How many multiverses are there in which chick A is unpecked? It ends up being $2^{98}$. The two neighboring chicks must peck away, and the other 98 can peck either way. Thus, for chick A, there are $2^{98}$ multiverses for which the (unpicked chick where that chick is A, multiverse) pair exists. But the unpicked chick can be any of the 100 chicks, and each of them are a chosen chick in \(2^{98}\) multiverses, so $X= 100 \cdot 2^{98}$.</p>

<p>Put together,
\(2^{100}\cdot Y = X = 100 \cdot 2^{98}\)
Which gives \(Y = 100\cdot \frac{2^{98}}{2^{100}} = 100\cdot \frac14=25\).</p>

<h2 id="canonical-math-example-2-of-2-handshake-lemma">Canonical Math Example (2 of 2): Handshake Lemma</h2>
<p>Another canonical example is the following, given first abstractly and then more concretely, with the real life example making the proof seemingly obvious.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Abstract: Let G be a simple graph (a set of vertices where each pair of vertices either has an edge between or not). Then the sum of all the degrees of vertices (number of edges into the vertex) of G is twice the number of edges.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But when you phrase it like this</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Handshake: A group of people are at a party. While there, some pairs of people shake hands. Let the degree of a person be the number of hands that person shook. Then, the sum of the degrees of all people is equal two twice the number of handshakes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A lot more obvious in the second one right? Clearly each handshake counts to two people’s degrees.</p>

<p>But the point of using “global” ideas is to measure one well-defined quantity in two ways because every well-defined quantity has a single value. Here, this would be done by counting the number of (V,E) pairs where V is a person and E is a handshake they partook in. If $X$ is the number of such pairs, then
\(\sum deg(V) = X = 2E\)
Since each vertex is in deg(V) such pairs, and each edge is in two such pairs.</p>

<h2 id="part-2">Part 2</h2>
<p>And now for a hard pivot. I don’t have <em>great</em> intuition about why this is the same as global combinatorics, but it feels similar?</p>

<h2 id="lottery-math-is-overcomplicated">Lottery Math is Overcomplicated</h2>
<p>The way that people usually claim that the lottery is a scam is by multiplying a bunch of numbers to find that the probability of winning. For examples, with a lot of calculations, the probability of winning the Mega Millions is “1 in 302,575,350”, and since the payout is less than 2$ * 302,575,350, you’d lose money on average. This is absurd though, it plays into the lottery’s abuse of human’s inability to intuitively grasp large numbers, and it’s so complicated that Khan Academy used it as a math exercise.</p>

<p>There’s a far simpler way to show that lotteries are a cash grab by the state. Instead of considering cash flow on the consumers end, consider it from the side of the government. (By law, lotteries must be run by the government) Even before taxes, a simple way to see that you cannot make money on it is the following quote:</p>

<p>“For Mega Millions (and Powerball) tickets, 50 percent of the sales goes to the prize pool. The remaining 50 percent is used to pay for the states’ retailer commissions, vendor fees, lottery administration, and the state beneficiaries or good causes of that state,” she told ABC News.</p>

<p>https://abcnews.go.com/US/mega-millions-lottery-lottery-money-states/story?id=58661412
Thus, on average, you will get back 50% of your ticket price. This is a lot simpler than figuring out the probabilities of each payout, and finding the expected payout that way.</p>

<p>But wait there’s more! When the payout finally happens, these massive sums of money are taxed at the highest interest bracket. The lottery is especially brilliant because it takes money from people who are usually lower income, and thus have untaxable money, and then put that together into one massive pot that can be taxed at the 50% maximum tax rate (federal + state taxes).</p>

<p>Somewhat expectedly, Vox says that</p>

<p>You hear it a lot: The lottery is a tax on people who are bad at math.</p>

<p>https://www.vox.com/identities/2016/1/13/10763268/lottery-poor-prey
But even the people who are “good at math” and calculate the probabilities are thinking about it in the wrong way. It is far simpler to consider it from the dual questions of “why does the government bother doing this?” and “what’s their profit margin?”</p>

<h2 id="economic-production-and-energy-consumption">Economic Production and Energy Consumption</h2>
<p>A surprising example of a nonmathematician using these ideas is Li Keqiang, the current Premier of the PRC. The story goes that in order to measure economic growth, he created his own list of indicators to track because he did not trust GDP estimates. The Li Keqiang index tracks railway cargo volume, electricity consumption, and loans disbursed by banks.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>This is another example of double counting because instead of calculating GDP as the sum of all economic activities, (calculating sum_{v\in G} deg v in the first example), one can simply record some economic indicators which should go up with economic activity instead. (like counting 2*</td>
      <td>E</td>
      <td>).</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Pyramid Schemes
Another fun double counting example is this scam that went around on instagram awhile ago. I happened across it when I went on instagram for the first time in a week.</p>

<p>From the internet. The ones that the people I follow posted were much flashier.
I’m looking for people to participate in a huge book exchange pyramid scheme. You can be anywhere in the world. All you have to do is buy your favorite book (just one) and send it to a stranger (I’ll send their details through in a private message).</p>

<p>You’ll receive roughly a maximum of 36 books back to you, to keep (we have sponsors or something). They’ll be favorite books from strangers around the world!</p>

<p>If you’re interested in taking part, please send a message saying “GULLIBLE”</p>

<p>My satirical version which I posted to my story. It got shoutouted/reposted by a Choate meme account 🙂
This is absurd by double counting. Firstly, this is obviously a pyramid scheme and some people will end up with no books because it’s impossible for everyone to receive more books than they buy.</p>

<p>Formally though, this violates the fact that in a directed graph, the sum of indegrees = number of edges = sum of outdegrees. (indegree is the number of arrows pointing to a graph, corresponding to buying a book for someone, and outdegree is the number of outward pointing arrows, corresponding to getting a book bought for you.)</p>

<p>Fermi Problems
Finally, this idea works pretty well in Fermi problems. Pretty much all Fermi problems where you don’t follow the most obvious thought process is a form of Double Counting. My favorite Fermi problem/solution pair is an answer to</p>

<p>“ How many hairs are present on your head?”</p>

<p>Instead of directly counting, we consider the balding process. Usually men lose hair and eventually go bald over the period from age 50 to age 80, so a period of 30 years. You don’t hear about balding men losing more hair than young people, and it seems reasonable to lose around 20 hairs a day. This gives</p>

<p>20 hairs/day * 30 years * 365 days/year = 219,000 hairs</p>

<p>The actual answer is ~100,000, which is surprisingly close to the estimate generated by considering balding men.</p>

<p>Conclusion
There’s a lot of olympiad math ideas which are extremely powerful in math, but also very useful in real life. There are people like Li Keqiang who have a decent informal grasp of ideas like counting in two ways. However, understanding the formal mathematical version makes the usage more conscious and therefore more powerful.</p>

<p>There’s two other ideas that I want to talk about, sharp ness and equality[1]. These are more philosophical, but they are also very powerful.</p>

<p>One thing I need to figure out is whether showing the informal examples first, and then the math, would be more accessible to a non-mathematical reader. I might try doing that in the post about sharpness or equality.</p>

<p>I guess leave a comment about which structure you would prefer?</p>

<p>[1] Unfortunately unaccessible if you’re not in OTIS 🙁 There doesn’t seem to be any good online source on what equality is, so this means that I’ll probably write about equality next.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>
<p>[1] A good formal introduction can be found in Chapter 7 of the <a href="https://web.evanchen.cc/textbooks/OTIS-Excerpts.pdf">OTIS Excerpts</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update," /><category term="essay" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[sabbe saṅkhārā aniccā (All conditioned things are impermanent) - Buddha]]></summary></entry></feed>